Hey , well , welcome to the commentary track for Prey .
I 'm the movie 's director , Dan Trachtenberg , and I 'm here with ...
Hi , I 'm Jeff Cutter , cinematographer .
Amber Midthunder . I play Naru .
The first thing we should mention , actually , is that logo .
At the very end of the fanfare , it went invisible - - The sound dropped out
and it went invisible like Predator cloaking .
And was so cool .
... pia mupitsl ikÜ kimai ,
I missed that .
- I really enjoyed that . - And we fought for it .
We fought for it and then they gave it to us .
And then at the last second , we added that line in the beginning ,
the prayer , the beginning of telling a story in Comanche .
And it felt like the tone was more serious and felt good and it felt like - -
The cloaking felt too genre , you know ? Too like , " Oh , tune in for Predator , "
when we were saying ,
" Actually , this movie is , you know , doing more things . "
- Didn 't it have lasers too ? - It did .
But maybe it 'll make its way in another movie , so ...
Someday .
Spoiler .
Any other movie can have that idea for free .
The opening , it was one-way scripted .
And if you remember , it originally started on an opening shot
of , like , a bug that got eaten by a fish and the fish got picked up by a hawk
- and then the hawk was shot down . - Yeah .
And then we were in the scene with you and your brother ...
- I loved that opening . - ... and all the guys .
The women in the background are composited in there .
That 's right .
- And the water was not blue . - The water was not blue .
Actually ?
- Yes . - I didn 't know that .
There was all the runoff at that time and it was all brown .
So it was muddy .
And then in the DI , Cody Baker fixed it for us .
Also , those flowers are more blue ?
They also were not there .
Is that right ? No . Yeah .
I don 't remember them there .
Yeah . Remember ? ' Cause you were digging up ...
Yeah , because there were only three that were there .
We were trying to make it special
- that the orange was different than the ... - That 's right .
When you do that later .
I remember seeing that and being like ,
" I don 't remember those people there . "
This was the first day of shooting .
It was . And I remember , um ...
I think I remember the crew being very confused at what was going on
" cause we had so many different iterations of , like , how to throw the tomahawk .
And , like , when I was going to miss and when it was going to hit .
Also figuring out the logistics of - - ' Cause we had so many different versions
and they have different weights and they don 't actually stick in the tree
" cause they 're not actually made of stone .
And I remember the crew - -
There was like this energy that everybody was like ,
" Oh , my God . Is she awful ? "
- Oh , oh , oh . - " Is she really bad at this ?
Is this movie going to be terrible ? "
I remember thinking like , " Oh , this is an interesting way to start . "
The expectation was you were supposed to be nailing it .
Yeah . Yeah .
And I could tell that they were like , " Oh , no . "
I think that was in your head .
- No , I was told later . - Really ?
Yes . ' Cause we had so many people in the film who - -
This was their first movie . Like , we have that internship program .
And so I remember somebody had asked another person ,
" Why are they doing it so many times ? "
And the other person had been like ,
" Because she 's supposed to hit the tree and she can 't quite get it . "
We should say something about Coco .
Although actually , ironically , this is the one scene ...
Where she was allowed to be herself ?
- Where this is not Coco . - It 's not ?
This one thing we had another dog
that was better at running ,
which sounds ironic because Coco was such a runner .
- Yeah . - But I think it was Tofu ,
was the name of this other dog playing Sarii .
- But this is definitely Coco . - This is Coco now .
- The star . Female dog . - Yeah , everyone loves her .
Yes . Female dog .
I loved this scene , this moment , this music and your vibe .
It 's a very winning moment in the movie where I feel like
it locks people like , " Okay , I 'll watch her , I 'll watch her in this . "
And this dog - - And everyone says , " This dog better not die . "
The moment in the test screenings
where I feel like everyone really connected with Naru
and was just here for her adventure .
- This scene did it for everybody . - Big time .
Why did we keep Sarii a boy when Coco was a girl ?
We don 't ever say .
- Sarii means dog . - I guess that 's true .
Sarii in Comanche means dog .
We loved the idea before we even knew the Comanche translation .
We just loved the idea of someone calling their dog , " Dog . "
That was just the fun of , " I like to call our dog , Dog . "
It 's a cute name for a dog in a movie .
This bit , this was also not in the original opening .
Um , and this is kind of what sold me - - Having this idea of going to title here
and for the longest time , it was like western themed .
Like an old , classic Hollywood show .
To see the copyright at the bottom and all that stuff is very old-fashioned .
And then we came to a certain point , where it 's like ,
" But the movie is not a western , so this is saying the wrong thing . "
So we affected it .
But we originally opened
on you guys down by the water and then the hunt ,
and there was no title situation ,
but that kind of sold me on the restructuring of the order .
I love the opening .
I was actually recently back home with my family
and they just put the movie on for the kids , and , uh - -
This was , like , my cousins and stuff .
We were in the other room and they were watching it in the living room
and I saw when the title comes on and I forgot about it .
- And I was like , " That 's cool . " - It has some cool vibes .
I like it .
You were sleeping .
[ Was waiting for it to circle back .
And this was also tailored a little bit .
Originally , all the other guys ,
all the other hunters , were here in the scene .
It was setting up a story about the drama between everyone
and wasn 't as focused as we realized we needed to be
on the sibling relationship , and your drive and what you 're after , so ...
I 'm ready for my kühtaamia .
You really think you 're ready ?
You wanna hunt something that 's hunting you ?
There are so many relationships and dynamics in this movie ,
you could just sit and explore any of those .
- It 's such a rich environment . - Mmm .
Just want to point out on the horses ,
Jhane Myers , our movie 's producer , is riding one of those horses .
And Cody Big Tobacco , right ?
- Is he the other guy ? - Yeah .
That makes sense . Cody Big Tobacco is like star horse rider .
- Like ... Yeah . - Indian relay .
- Yeah . He 's a champion . - He wins .
He 's one of the best Indian relay riders , like , ever .
Wow .
He 's one of the actors in the movie . Also , that was a real fish .
- Just want to say that . - Really ?
- Yes . - Not right now though .
Can 't be , " cause he would have gone for it , no ?
No . That was part of the problem .
The magic of movies .
Remember when we thought this was just coverage ?
We didn 't think this was gonna be one take .
And Angela tried . You tried very hard to , like , have , you know ...
Like , " Oh , it 's actually just - - Works just playing it . "
It 's the fact that you stay in the shot for that long
that actually allows the film to breathe and I think that 's why it works so well .
I agree . I was nervous that it wasn 't holding , you know ?
The dog looks at the camera a couple of times too .
I was worried it would take a while .
Petsü .
- That was also a real fish . - That 's fake .
You cut real , and then we swapped it ...
- Because she couldn 't have - - - ... because she wasn 't in the shot .
So she had to pick up the fake one
' cause otherwise , she would eat the real one .
But there was one time that she stole it as I was cutting it .
- She bit the tail and ran away . - Everyone like , " Oh , no . "
Everybody freaked out because the bones would hurt her .
One of the times I was walking , she grabbed it out of my hand also .
To be fair , wasn 't she just recently adopted from a shelter ?
This is not a trained - - I mean , she was by the time she was in the movie , but ...
She was not a movie dog before .
Amber 's like , " - ish . " "
Yeah , we keep saying not trained ,
but actually , props to her trainers .
Ray Beal , in particular ,
for only having a couple of months to get her into shape ,
and it was very challenging .
But she comes off great in the movie and is an awesome dog .
I almost got a deer with it .
Yeah . Well , we can 't eat " almost . "
My girl , you are good at so many other things .
Why do you want fo hunt ?
Because you all think that I can 't
Fun fact , this was one of my audition scenes .
Yes . In fact , it was a scene that you guys did wordless .
An audition scene that you did wordless as well .
This is the one .
- Yeah , it was beautiful . - This is our first .
Yeah , this is my audition scene and then the test scene
that we did in English Comanche
- and the famous " no words . " - No words .
Which made the Amber choice undeniable for the movie .
- That was cool . - It was really fun .
That was a really cool moment .
That was when I described , I think , our ability to not speak to each other .
- You and I. - Yeah .
' Cause I remember you just walked around the corner
and I was still standing there , and you just stopped walking ,
we looked at each other , and you were like , " That - - "
And you , like , nodded .
And I was like , " Yeah , that was - - " And you were like , " Yeah . "
I was like , " Okay , cool . "
So this was a fun little - - This was from a different scene .
" Something from nothing . " That 's what I would call this scene .
Yeah . There used to be a montage at one point in the movie
of the Predator assembling all of his weapons .
That shot came at the end of that montage .
And then we were restructuring the movie
and wanted to introduce the Predator earlier .
I think , Angela , you had - -
Like , " We could use that shot at the end with him rising up
and just extend it , and add a cool Predator ship floating by . "
It was pretty much just an empty shot - -
Piece of film for a long time
that originally occurred much later in the film ,
but was repurposed , as many things were in this movie .
Um ...
Then with the help of visual effects , yeah ,
I turned it into a Predator .
Those were not my hands .
Yeah , those were little pickups to emphasize ,
so people could track the flower .
That was from one of our reshoots , right ?
Did you remember that those weren 't your hands ,
or were you looking at them going , " Those aren 't my hands . "
Every time I see it , I have the thought of ,
" I don 't think those are my hands . " And then I remember .
I 'm like , " Are those my hands ? "
And then I remember that you told me they 're not .
Itsee .
- Hina ? - A lion . It took Puhi .
We gotta find him .
So right there , we cut out a giant scene with Julian ,
our War Chief , who was awesome - -
Giving a real drill sergeant-esque pep talk
to the hunters to go out there and kick ass .
And it opened on the shot , pushing it on his back with all the scars .
It was super cool , but the movie just needed the momentum to get into this .
It 's funny seeing even the stuff from the beginning
because we had mixed in the reshoot .
Like there are pieces of the scene at the river .
It 's so funny that that was the first day of shooting .
Then we did half of that scene also , just , like , intercut with each other
from reshoots that were like nine months or ten months later .
Some crazy amount of time later in a different country .
- A totally different time . - Yeah .
When you were coming down that thing and I was like ,
" You gotta do something cool with the thing . "
And you were like , " I can 't even walk down this . "
And all of us are crawling to get up just these little mini hills .
And you 're like , " Yeah . Yeah , I 'll be cool . "
- And you 're trying not to fall . - I was like , " For sure . "
It was one of the many times that we started
where you would be like , " Just try to not fall down . " "
Definitely didn 't make it easy by always picking treacherous terrain
- for every scene . - I didn 't want to .
I didn 't want to go into those places , but we had to .
- I will . - I know .
' Cause you have fo .
This was born out of the original opening of the movie ,
where we were sort of doing this chain of the natural world
that the Predator comes in looking for the alpha
and it became better suited tracking the Predator alongside Naru ,
putting the sequence in the middle , and then making it all more menacing .
There 's a little bit of a background plate that we shot ,
but it 's , for the most part , CG .
I like that that made its way back in there because I really liked that .
I remember when you told me that that wasn 't the opening anymore .
I was bummed .
Because you need concept to be in the movie .
It 's very much a thematic notion , who 's on top .
And who 's seen as on top versus who actually is on top .
Oh , good . The dog found shit .
- We 're not looking for wolves . - It 's not wolf .
The CG leaf in the foreground .
The whole time in the frame you could see there was already blood on that leaf
and I really wanted that to be a reveal .
So they added a leaf in the foreground to not give it away . Yeah .
This is a definite throwback to the original , here .
He 's breathing .
Petsü .
- Is this Sam ? - Yeah .
We told the actor playing Puhi
on the ground that Amber had actually eaten the flowers
and so that he had to do that as well , and he actually does ingest them .
Because they were technically edible .
But I was like , " I don 't - - I 'm not gonna eat this . "
So I took it and he was like , " Do I eat them or no ?
Like what do I do ? "
And I was like , " Well , I ate mine , and so I think you got to eat them .
Like that 's how it works in the world .
In this Predator world , you have to eat them . "
And he was like , " I do ? "
And I was like , " Yeah . " And I was feeding them to him .
So I gave it to him , and then I chugged the water down
and he swallowed them . And then I was like ,
" By the way , I spit mine out . "
- You did tell him ? - Yeah , I told him later .
- You 're putting them in . - They 're in there .
- I 'm trying to save him . - Yeah , and he 's - -
- You could see him actually eating them . - And not enjoying .
It 's funny ' cause he was chewing .
And I was like , " Don 't chew them . "
But then I think I told him after the first take ' cause I felt bad .
- Yeah . - It 's so glamorous .
- I 'm coming with you . - / can handle the lion .
No , it 's not just the lion .
Why is Puhi alive ? There 's something that scared the cat away from its den .
I 've got this .
Stay with Puhi . He needs your help too .
We don 't have time to waste talking . We need to get him home .
ManamÜsohi
We shot this backwards or something , right ?
This was the first scene we did with torches ,
and we had hidden these little LEDs in the torches ...
Mm-hmm .
... because there 's a couple of other wide shots coming .
And I remember telling Amber and everyone else ,
" You 've got to hold these torches a certain way .
You 've got to hold them so that they light your face
but they don 't go to the camera . " And it was a bit of an ordeal .
Then we did this scene .
But the other scene was first , and I remember overhearing Amber say ,
" Again with the torches . Now I gotta hold - - "
But for the acting scenes , we didn 't use the LEDs
because I didn 't want it to be something that interfered , so ...
- Because of that comment ? - No , no . Because ...
Because she 's such a problem .
... to be fair to Amber , yeah ,
I don 't want it to be something that distracts from acting .
In the other scenes , I felt like you 're just running .
- It wasn 't like intense acting . - It 's funny .
I think that intense acting would have been easier
because what it was was the ... There 's - - It 's coming up ,
- Corvin goes - - Paaka . - You 're chasing after .
We 're , like , running up that hill ,
and then I go and I 'm chasing after him and I 'm sprinting up that hill behind him ,
and you couldn 't see anything .
So it 's , like , you have the fire and you 're running ,
and the fire is face level , SO you 're running
and the flame is next to you
or , like , in front of you . The LED is in your face .
But that meant we couldn 't see anything .
Running up the hill and you 're like , " Just sprint as fast as you can . "
And then I 'm trying . We 're sprinting , trying not to fall ,
and I 'm running , and then you 're like ,
" Also , I don 't want to see the LED .
I can see the LED . "
I was like - - It was just a lot of things happening all at once .
But we were nicer than that .
Sort of .
Just kidding . Yes , it was not you yelling .
- But it was because you were far away . - Yeah , yeah , yeah .
So the yelling was not meanness , it was just that everybody ...
- To hear . Distance . - Distance .
The function of your location .
Exactly . Also , it was like , what ?
Three o 'clock in the morning .
This evolved a little bit too .
There used to be this shimmering Predator there
and then we rearranged things
and it was too soon to - -
The Predator should not be this close to them and , you know ?
Right . So here you can 't see where you 're going at all .
It makes sense .
- Now , I understand . - Yeah , I get it .
But such cool shots , so it was worth it .
Yeah .
I got up there . I was like , " Corvin , can you see anything ? "
And he was like , " No , I feel like I 'm gonna fall . "
So all this stuff was right next to the tall grass field
which allowed us to shoot ...
Because we wanted the whole tall grass sequence to be at dusk ,
and dusk is only a matter of hours
and not enough time to actually shoot a scene .
We , I think , cleverly figured out a way
in which we could just do two scenes over multiple nights .
So we had multiple , you know , at-bats at shooting a scene at dusk .
So it was like a week . Five dusk shots , five dusk setups
and then five bites of this apple .
The tall grass is the one later .
Yeah , where you guys are hiding in the grass and - -
- You and Harlan . - The one from the trailer .
The one in the first teaser , exactly .
Do we talk about this , Jeff ?
This shot of this tree . The arguments .
The 15 % of real tree that 's there .
Right . That 's true too .
And , uh - - Against green screen out in the real world , which ...
On location , but filled with green screens .
... looking back , feels silly .
But it was for that reason , it was so that we could shoot this
- and get more dusk stuff . - Sure .
Always having a little bit of reality is nice .
Yeah , agree .
I also just wanna mention this was a reshoot
on Taabe 's line - - on Dakota 's line .
Dakota Beavers plays Taabe . Amazing . First ever acting thing ever .
When the lion comes , you tell that thing ,
" This Is as far as you go .
No more . "
Especially in that moment , and a few of the others ,
like , driving home that , " This is as far as I go . "
Which came from an email Jhane sent me at one point about - -
It was a Comanche saying of - - Someday this should be in a movie also - -
Is what it would be is , when they were in battle
and they were done for ,
they would take an arrow , take their breechcloth ,
tether themselves to the ground and say , " This is as far as I go . No more . "
As if , " You 're not pushing me back any further , I will stand my ground . "
That would 've been cool if he did that in the movie .
I know . Trust me .
I mean , it was a - - Well , it was reshoots when I - -
I was looking through old emails and I saw that . I was like , " Oh , my God . "
So that tree was green screen behind it ,
even though we were on location ,
but we were still far out in the woods .
We had to have the green screen .
Because the whole design of that sequence
was to have Amber and the lion silhouetted .
Because otherwise , if there 's something behind it - -
They wouldn 't be able to pull them out .
The sequence is designed
not so much to be lighting you guys on the tree
as much as to see you silhouetted against the night sky .
So why did we not do that on a stage ?
One , stage space was limited .
And there is still a fair amount of it that the camera 's looking down .
And we would have had to have built a whole bunch of ground .
- And that ridge . - Yeah .
Oh . This is lots of wires .
This was a bit that we thought
we were gonna rely heavily on your stunt double for , Tammy .
Amazing . However , crazily enough , that 's you .
Like , you owned that tree . You were really - -
Do you feel like you enjoyed it ?
I do . I love wires . I love wirework .
I 'm a little air monkey .
It 's too bad that the audience can 't see
what we saw when we were shooting ,
which was the person pretending to be the lion , as the reference ,
- climbing on all fours on the branch . - In gray .
They had drawn a kitty nose on him
and little whiskers on his cheeks as a joke .
And he had - - I don 't remember if he even had a joke , like , little ears .
Little cat ears on top .
Which is what I was looking at for that whole thing .
Your brother carried you home .
Wha - - What about the lion ?
- Taabe went after it - Okay .
! have to find him .
No , you need fo rest .
/ Aka .
Drink this tea .
Ihka .
Puhi survived because of your medicine .
There 's something else out there . Taabe needs my help .
If your brother needed you , he wouldn 't have brought you back here .
You think the reason for kühtaamia is to prove you can hunt ,
but there 's only one reason .
To survive .
Taabe kima ! Taabe kima !
Did you always want to - -
Like , did you guys always want to do real on location and stuff ,
or were you , like , open to the idea of shooting on stages ?
Creatively ? Yes .
Personal life , no . I wanted to be on stage .
This , also , by the way - - A great fake build of a lion , I think .
- There 's no CG there . - It is built well .
And it just makes him seem so strong . He just throws it down .
It is heavy . It 's heavy .
It 's legit . Yeah . Yeah .
Did Alec build that as well as the Predator stuff ?
We should give him the shout-out .
Yeah , Alec Gillis and Tom Woodruff Jr. of ADI ,
who have worked on every great movie you 've ever seen ,
and all the Alien and Predator movies , practically , if not actually ,
did all the creature stuff in this movie .
Including even the little pneumatic snake we saw earlier
and the buffalo we 'll eventually see ,
and obviously , all the awesome Predator stuff .
This , once again , was another great scene
with the War Chief addressing everyone ,
and there were just a few details in it that - - I think there was a lot of , like ,
" Well , aren 't they going to mourn the loss of the people that died ? "
It all was very tricky .
And then Angela found a way to craft a sequence
just with this music and no words .
And so it all just felt way more emotional than it was before .
Naru .
Much more linked to Naru 's POV .
- Her experience of the situation . - We were always trying to be - -
Well , not always , but certain scenes - - be in the bubble , we called it , with Naru ,
and present things from her perspective , which is very interesting .
But also , getting rid of a lot of the dialogue .
There were a lot of cool shots
that I couldn 't figure out how to fit into a dialogue sequence .
So , some fun rack focuses and things that in a dialogue scene wouldn 't work .
But we could throw those in and make a montage and that 's always ...
I will never refuse the exercise of making a montage
- out of something that 's a dialogue scene . - We took advantage of that .
- Yeah . Yeah . - Terrence Malick .
Yeah . Like every day with Dan started with , like , " What if we - - "
Like , " I 'm in . Let 's do it , let 's try it . " It didn 't always work ,
- but yeah , it was a lot of fun . - Yeah , I love , Angela ,
how you stripped everything back as much as you could ,
which is something that we were also doing , crafting this film .
It 's just like stripping back and stripping back
and getting to the - - Just the really , really important stuff .
Something like this - -
I feel like this film could easily just be sensory overload in every scene
because there 's so much going on . The environment is huge . Predator is huge .
There 's a lot of action , and just pared back .
And its essence ,
you know , sometimes just going to its essence was the right recipe .
I don 't know if you guys remember that - -
The night that we got shut down when we were shooting this fire .
The high winds ?
I don 't remember it totally because I fell asleep
when a lot of the catastrophe was happening .
- It was like one of those ... - I 'm so offended by that .
Well , not during your acting scenes ,
it was while they were rigging lights
and they were falling apart .
I 'm just offended that you got to sleep .
Dan , I think , might be a really good napper
- because he 's - - Yeah . - I crash .
There were a few times , we were working on something
and I turn around and on that couch behind me ,
Dan 's just having a little snooze .
This is one of my favorite shots .
I 'm known for that . Yeah , I love this .
One of my favorite shots in the movie .
What happened when we got shut down ? I don 't remember .
- We went home . - But why did we - -
You may not have been there
because it may have been just shooting partyers and stuff .
Maybe you weren 't . I mean , you were there all those evenings there .
- Yeah . - I was always there .
I want to mention - -
No , but they may - - they actually probably cut you loose to have - -
So we had to turn around .
Maybe it was a little piece , right ? When I was getting - -
Literally , everyone part - - You walk away .
Yeah . Yeah . Yeah .
77 they don 't see ,
we 'll show them .
Kima .
I want to mention here ...
- Yeah , I love this scene ... - Yeah , it 's really beautiful .
... and I love the look .
Thematically what it is ,
but I really wanna mention , the score 's done by Sarah Schachner who I found - -
I was playing Assassin 's Creed Valhalla
while we were prepping the movie , and I was like - -
How many games ' influence ?
So we could list the number of games that influence this movie .
There 'll be more later .
And I was like , " God , this music is beautiful . Who did this ? "
And I saw Sarah 's name and I wasn 't familiar with it .
Then did a little bit of a dive on her
and found other games that she had scored that I loved .
And she was incredible .
And we temp scored the whole movie
with very modern , atmospheric , drony , brooding .
Very - - A lot of Sicario score was used .
I loved the idea of doing a movie set in a time period
where the music didn 't necessarily
always reflect the music you expect to hear in that time period .
But that sequence where she sets out , we had temped with the score
from , like , Maleficent or Snow White and the Huntsman
or , you know , really big fantasy .
Everyone was always bunked by it , but I loved it .
I was like , " I can 't believe we 're making a movie
that could have score like this . This is incredible .
We could have something that feels that anthemic . "
And Sarah found a way to have a score for this movie
that often times was more modern and not what you expect .
But then these moments that are ginormous ,
heavy and inspiring and all those things .
It just was , like , a great epic theme .
And it was one - - I remember when we heard it for the first time .
I mean , I just - - It was on repeat .
Constantly I 'm like , " Oh , this is the movie . This is the movie . "
- I know how excited you were by it too . - Oh , man . Yeah . Beyond .
Yeah , and her score - -
It 's so many different genres within this film .
I mean , the Predator has electronic elements .
He has cello , and then we have that sweeping ,
you know , organic orchestral thing for her journey .
I mean , it 's a testament to Sarah 's versatility .
She really knocked it out of the park .
This scene is all largely electronic
and sometimes when you think it 's electronic ,
it 's actually cello , and she specialized in that .
And when you hear cello , it 's - - I think it 's all her .
- She performs it all herself . - She plays a lot of these .
She has an upright bass and she does amazing things .
There were so many times where I thought ,
" This part with electric guitar . " And she 's like , " No , that 's cello . "
Oh , wow .
Because she uses instruments in unexpected ways .
That 's a build .
I think it 's augmented , but that 's another Alec and Tom build , I believe .
This was all shot in California . Most of the movie was shot in Alberta ,
but that sequence was done in California .
Had to remove a few power lines back there , but ...
This makes no sense , but it works .
That was so ...
You 're holding that , right ?
- That was one of our - - - Do we flick it up ?
It was both .
So , the challenging thing with that stuff was the terrain .
So we had practiced .
I mean , as soon as I got cast , you were like ,
" Always have something on you that you can , like , twiddle or twirl
or just get good with your hands . " "
You were like , " Even if it 's just a pencil . "
So I was always doing stuff like that .
I think we sent you a prop thing .
Yeah . And then I asked if you could send me some
and none of them were that .
But it was still - - At least I had something .
And then at home , we had throwing axes anyway .
So I was like , " Okay , I 'll - - " But those are sharp .
So I was like , " Okay , I 'm gonna figure out weight and dimensions and stuff . "
But that is so much of what maneuvering it is about ,
and then the terrain .
So , in the training camp , that was what I was doing .
Let me just say ,
I think you made a couple of those .
I don 't know if it sticked in the tree , but you definitely - -
You did a couple that nailed it , that bounced ' cause it hit the tree ...
More than a couple .
... and had a couple returns too that were - - Yeah .
It was because - - The challenges were - -
Because we did that , that was like so much of what I did during the training camp ,
was just working with the tomahawk .
We would stick it in cardboard boxes and then I would pull it
because we were also learning how it would move
and what I had to do to - - How hard I had to yank it ,
how fast it would come at me , where I have to catch it .
What looks cool .
And then , when we got out there ,
the rope was getting stuck in the tall weeds , and like ...
Things you can 't expect ' cause , " We 're in the elements . "
That would make it hard .
So I spent all that time getting it in real life ,
and then we had to figure it out differently on the day .
I remember scouting this location , snapping on snowshoes .
This is the snowshoe location .
The snowshoe location .
Because when we scouted , it was winter so we could shoot in the summer .
Went , " Yeah , I guess this will look good when this all melts . "
It was so beautiful .
It was also really scary " cause that is a sheer cliff right there .
And it is far down .
- Also , that was teeth brushing . - That was teeth brushing .
We were hell-bent on having - -
I 've always wanted to do a period movie where you see someone do something mundane
and understand how it was done then . What was it ?
- It was a reed or something . - Mm-hmm .
That was something that I really respected about one of our first conversations .
You were like , " Any time you have any ideas
or anything to put in there , especially about day-to-day stuff ,
like how people brush their hair , how you brush your teeth ,
what you sleep on , things like that . I love all those things
and please incorporate that kind of stuff . "
I think that 's so interesting and I thought that that was so cool to do .
So this sequence was not always in the movie .
It was a reshoot to kind of do what the original Predator movie did .
Train people to understand that this guy is a trophy hunter
and that he 's there looking for the alpha and for the coolest trophy .
And so we concocted this scene
that alludes to the scene that was in the first movie
where you just see a really cheesy ' 80s poof of smoke
and then a skull . And we thought , " Now we have the ability ,
let 's show , like , what that stuff does . "
So we developed this cool effect to reveal the skull ,
and then find a really iconic image of him in that mountain .
So some of these are builds .
Yeah , the first three or four .
- Yeah , that one , I know . - That one for sure .
It 's an ADI build . Horrifying .
This scene made me really sad .
Really - - Yeah .
Yeah . Those are real .
I mean , not - - I mean , those are builds . Those are practical .
I mean , it 's gnarly .
It 's a good - - I don 't want to misspeak ,
but I know someone on the team there at ADI
had worked on the triceratops
in Jurassic Park , that practical triceratops ,
and may have been the person that did these buffaloes .
Oh , wow .
I think this prayer was something that got given to me that day .
Very likely .
Same thing with the Comanche that I spoke to the dog in the last scene .
All of it because we were trying to be as accurate as possible .
And Jhane was always getting in touch with the language department
and making sure that it was right .
Sometimes that would come down to the wire .
We were always trying to figure out where we could put in Comanche
and what had to be in English .
And so , a lot of it was you or Jhane or even me being like ,
" Could we add a Comanche line here ? " But that would also mean
I had to learn a Comanche saying right then .
- Accurate statement . - Yeah .
Dane DiLiegro playing the Predator .
Great guy , great work ethic .
Made this thing very unique .
And one of the cooler entries into movie monster legacy - -
His performance , I think .
We will see much more of him . Okay . Here we go .
- We have stories , right ? - Oh , my goodness .
Okay .
This is - - Do you remember which one ?
Well , we shot this for five days .
Yes . We shot this for five days ,
because I 've heard you talk about this in many interviews .
You enter and we can shoot a little bit with you in it , and then that 's it .
Yeah , once I 'm in the mud , I 'm in the mud .
Once you 're in the mud and then you get cleaned up .
- So we can 't do multiple - - - The day is done .
We can 't do multiple - -
So we do everything from this angle , right ?
Everything from the side of you entering .
Here 's a shot from a different angle . We can 't do those on the same day .
Those would be on different days ' cause the cameras would see each other .
We did have multiple cameras , right ? It would be two or something .
From the same side .
So it 's front back profile . So it 's probably three days .
- And overhead . - Overhead , right .
Or was that later ?
Overhead could have been done at the same time .
And I understand that that mud was pretty smelly ,
not the best , or ...
Could you smell it from where you guys were sitting ?
I tried to be far enough away .
When you get close to it , you - -
And as I 've mentioned before ,
it wasn 't smelly , you 'd walk around . You 'd have no idea .
As soon as the first person entered it ,
like as soon as flesh touched it , for whatever reason ,
it emitted something .
Opened the vacuum or something .
It was that covering layer that would kind of seal it in .
Then Amber would go in and be like , " Ooh , this is awful . "
It 's like a pot of soup when it 's sitting there
versus , like , when you stir it .
And you couldn 't really hear .
I was kind of doing charades to like ... You know ?
Rich was great in your ear trying to tell you what to do .
No , I didn 't have an earwig .
I had earplugs because that mud couldn 't get in my ears .
So we were yelling at you like crazy .
At one point , you came out and you hid ,
and you were just screaming at me .
So you could get out of the mud .
You were not screaming at me .
Let 's be careful with our words .
You are not a screamer .
You were speaking loudly so that I could hear you .
And also trying to charade me around , and I do remember - -
- Yeah , this was disgusting . - Yeah .
I remember when I did this and then a little glop fell on my forehead
and I was like , " That 's the grossest thing ever . "
And I think it was the first time we had done all the struggle
and I was like , " How do I get out ? " And you were like , " Just get out . "
You 're like , " I don 't know , crawl . "
" I don 't know if I can . It 's too heavy . "
And you were like , " Yeah , go ! "
Because we were shooting that .
- So I wanted to see you struggle . - Actually struggle .
And I did get out .
- I was very proud of that . - Was it cold as well ?
- Yes , it was so cold . - Is it cold ?
It was cold and it was scratchy
because all of the plants in there .
I could feel like , " Am I getting little cuts
and are they really dirty ? "
I remember thinking that . Look how thick it is .
So it got all in my - - I was wearing a wet suit
which did not end up really helping , it just made everything heavier .
All the weapons , my moccasins , everything .
My hair got so heavy and weighted down
" cause all that water and all that mud went into my clothes .
This was designed , intentionally , to be like ,
" Oh , if you 've seen a Predator movie before ,
you assume she 's in the mud .
That 's how it 's not going to see her . "
And then , the second later , she 's washing herself off and we go ,
" That 's not - - This movie is gonna do something different . "
There you are .
Now we have the bear scene .
This was , I think , one of the more challenging things we did
because of the location .
We had to helicopter equipment in because it was so inaccessible .
Yeah . And take a raft across the river to get to the - -
Oh , wow .
And I 'll just say , the first iteration in screenplay
was you and Predator both watching a bear attacking ,
seeing who 's the victor , and the Predator sort of analyzing .
A lot of it had to be adjusted per budget . We couldn 't afford that many effect shots ,
and that 's where the idea came from to set so much of it in the beaver dam .
" Cause it would mean we only saw things in pieces ,
and just have a few shots , and this and that .
Which ended up being a way better sequence than what it was .
But all came from having limited funds .
There 's very economic use of how and when we see the bear .
I remember you being on top there and you having your phone out .
And we had no reception there
and I was like , " What is going on ?
How does she - - What is she looking at on her phone ? "
And then one time I was over your shoulder ,
and you had your phone out and you had the script ,
and we were giving you new things all the time .
And I was like , " That 's what she 's doing on her phone . "
But then you would hide it , you hid it under a rock .
You always had fun little hiding spots .
Yeah , I always had it on me . Sometimes it was in my tunic .
A lot of times it was in my bag , because that was a functional bag .
Sometimes I hid it in my moccasin .
- Oh . Interesting . - Mm-hmm .
Which was hard because that was really tied on there .
Behind a rock , under a leaf . Behind a tree .
I was taking lots of pictures . I was looking at the script .
You were taking pictures too .
- I took a lot of pictures . - Which is great .
So , this interior was in a tank , all on blue screen .
Mm-hmm . Outside still .
Oh , yeah , outside . And was this cold ?
I think this was - - Did they heat this or was this cold as well ?
I think it might have been heated
but it was really cold .
Watching it now ,
I 'm still a little confused why it had to be a tank .
Versus ?
Just being a set . Piece of set .
- We didn 't need the water element . - Because I dive into the ...
I sort of agree with you .
- So far , we don 't - - - It was massive overkill .
I think it 's her coming up .
- That one . - That one little piece .
- I feel like we could have - - Yeah . - Massive overkill .
I feel like I said that a lot too .
- You probably did . - Okay .
When we were doing that , I was out in the middle of that tank
and you guys were in the tent .
So Rich , our first AD , was relaying your notes and the beats .
Yelling - - Nobody was yelling at me .
It was outside .
I had to speak loudly . We had to yell .
He was giving me so many , like , " Okay , look up . Brave , scary ... "
You get so lost in it , we would go for so long .
We would do such long takes .
And so when I ended up seeing that sequence
and understanding how clear the beats were ,
they were not that clear when we were shooting ,
and I remember being like ,
" Oh , my gosh , is that what I was looking at ?
' Cause I would have done that different . "
And especially when the bear lays down next to me , dead .
I was like , " That 's what I was supposed to look at ? "
We were calling them out as you were doing it live .
Because that got out of order and that was so chaotic
that I obviously knew what the scene was and what the beats were .
But I didn 't know where we were all the time .
- For that shot , that 's why . - That 's tank too . That 's why .
I know , but did we have to ?
- But she goes - - - This is not tank .
- This is not tank . - This is real river .
Which is crazy . And thank you for doing that .
It 's a great shot and , you know , couldn 't have done it without you .
- It was really fun . - Honestly .
Well , we couldn 't have done it without your moxie to do it .
It was fun . That river was so cold .
This is not you and this is not even our movie .
I don 't even know if I should say . This is footage from our VFX supervisor
who also worked on Call of the Wild , which is also a 20th Century Fox movie .
- This is back to us . - This is real river again .
This is fake Amber . Real river .
- No , this is CG arms . Wait ... - What ?
Yes . Your arms were covered in wet suit .
That 's right .
You had a long wet suit on
and we needed to use the shot because , you know ...
- The river was so cold . - We couldn 't do it to you .
It was all glacial runoff water . It was so , so cold .
So we had an incredible , incredible effects artist painted over ...
Made the wet suit look like skin .
... through 2D compositing , made flesh out of your arms .
- Oh . - Absolutely incredible .
I did wonder about that . I did wonder how that happened .
- What are you doing here ? - Looking for you .
Your brother sent us fo bring you home .
Where is he ?
Searching for you on the other side of the pass .
Where are you going ?
- I saw it . - Saw what ?
I saw what left those tracks .
- The bear ? - There was a bear ,
but there was something else , and it was huge .
[ Couldn 't see it until it was covered in blood , but it looked like - -
like a mupitsl .
You saw a monster from a children 's story ?
It fought and killed a bear with its hands , easily .
How come it didn 't kill you ?
Stop !
You 're going home .
Enough !
This is awesome .
- This fight ? - This is all you .
And this is you and Stormee , who plays Wasape ,
the guy who 's beating you up .
Or trying to . That 's Cody Big Tobacco .
- That punch is brutal . - Mm-hmm .
You guys really - -
It 's such a less genre-y fight , you know ?
I mean , it 's so nice to see in the movie and yeah , you 're just so terrific in it .
You wanna leave ? Then leave .
We 're going home .
Shall we talk about the thermal camera ?
That we actually shot with a real thermal camera ...
- Yeah , go for it . - ... like the , uh , original Predator ,
so that we wanted to have that as much in-camera as possible .
Although , we did have the same problems they had .
Which was if it was too hot , you wouldn 't actually get the - -
Everything would be red and yellow .
Yeah , we sort of - - The production of this movie disproves
the way that the Predator works .
Because as we learned when we 're shooting ,
when you put on the thermal vision , everything is hot
because we 're outside and the hot sun is baking the ground .
So the ground is also hot .
So we had to , like , cool off and do some other filtration .
Shoot things later , or early or late ,
before or after it was too hot .
Yeah . This was interesting , where we would talk to an adviser
about how , like , going to the bathroom might have worked .
You did ?
That was the idea of being in a tree
and squatting and holding yourself .
Oh , is he supposed to be up in a tree ?
No , he 's not up in the tree .
When you 're crouching , you have some support holding the tree .
It was researched .
Which I always thought was really clever .
I was like , " Yeah , that is better than just crouching . "
Remember we talked a lot about phases of makeup .
I 've always loved this aspect of your performance .
We see you so much with your face paint , and then we 're in the section
of the movie where it 's gone and then when it comes back .
Yeah , it 's interesting because there 's no colors
and the design doesn 't change really .
Yeah , we had a lot of conversations about how to ,
I think , kind of express or represent , like , a different portion of the film .
And we kind of broke it up into chapters that way
of marking Naru 's journey by the face paint .
And what the face paint is doing . Is it there ? What is it made of ?
Because later , then I put it back on , but it 's made of ash .
Yep . I remember going back and forth on
is it cool that you would start out with none ?
And then , you put it on later and go , " Now here she is . "
Or is it cool that you have it and then you 're without it ?
So it feels like you 're more bare . That was the nature of the conversation .
- I like the way we did it . - Yeah , I agree .
Do you remember when we got in a fight over what color it was ?
- And who wins that fight ? - I do . I do .
- Uh , I definitely did not win . - Yeah .
I mean , I guess you were not wrong - -
- You thought it was blue , right ? - I thought it was blue .
You said it was black . But I think there 's blue in the black and there was .
It was green .
Right , there was green in the black .
Also , we enhanced that in color later with Cody .
Hey . Cut me loose .
Stay down .
I wanna shout out - -
First of all , I love that reveal and Tymon - -
So , that 's Cody Big Tobacco who we mentioned before ,
and Tymon Carter .
We 've missed it , but when he yells , just before they clash ...
- His war cry . - ... and his war cry is un - -
It gave me chills every time I saw it . We were all like ,
" Whoa , this is like - - We 're really doing this . "
Yeah , I remember everybody being amazed at how well their fight - -
I don 't know , when finally there was the take that they were really ready
to let loose , kind of , the first time , and they could just go through it ,
how much those two brought it .
Very upsetting because of how he performed it .
I didn 't imagine it all being that way .
That was a really cool sequence to shoot .
And you flipping the thing . When you flipped the thing to - -
- Which was very , you know ... - The tomahawk .
... that was one of the first ideas I had .
I was like , " She 's gonna do something cool to get - - "
I just wanted you to have little flourishes
that made it feel like Naru has this dexterity that is special .
I didn 't think you were gonna do that .
We were gonna move on right before the big storm came .
- We had to - - - Yeah .
That was another one that I kept - -
We would practice it , and I would get it every time .
And as soon as we got there , I couldn 't do it .
And you said , " I just need one more . "
You gave me a really serious look .
I 'm like , " If she does this , this will be the story we tell .
Where she gave me this serious look and it actually worked . "
I didn 't think it was actually gonna - -
Those moments never work for me in my life ,
but maybe Amber 's special .
And you did it .
And it worked and I was like , " Oh , my God . "
The camera , you know , wraps around as you do .
I could not believe that all worked .
Cody Big Tobacco here also had a wire stunt that he did himself .
Mm-hmm . He was actually hired as a stunt man
- to do the stunt , you know . - That 's right .
- Then it 's like , " He 's great . " - That 's the wire .
But he had a better wire in the beginning whenever I 'm crawling
from behind the log that 's kind of in the back .
- And he 's thrown . - Yeah , he 's lift - -
He 's , like , launched up into the air upside down and then over the log .
And I remember him doing that and he was just so amped up .
This was the tall grass sequence we were referring to earlier .
We were able to do all that at the right time of day .
- And that we grew that grass . - We grew that grass .
What ?
We could not find a field that had the grass we wanted .
So in prep , in the very beginning , we said , " This is where we want to be , "
and they planted all that grass .
Our production designer , Kara Lindstrom ,
and our greens , Tom Green - -
Our greens guy 's name was Tom Green - - did the science , worked it out .
It was a real nail-biter because the whole point is tall grass ,
- not just grass . - Yeah .
They 're like , " We hope it 's between this and this ,
but it 's nature and we don 't know . "
It was such a nail-biter the whole time .
" But is it gonna ? Because the sequence is dependent on that . "
- Crazy . - And it worked out .
It was very scary .
Also , we were by a real river that day .
And I remember Harlan , who plays Itsee , in the tall grass ,
- he made you an arrow . - I still have it .
- Really ? - Still have it .
He built you an arrow out of rocks and a stick that he found
and some bark that he used to tie it together .
He posted on Instagram recently , the construction of it .
Yeah , that 's the thing that I have .
You 're like , " It 's still in my house . "
Regardez ici .
Une femme ?
Qu 'est-ce qu 'elle fait ici ?
Je vais la porter .
Elle va nous ralentir .
Non . Par la facon qu 'elle courait , Je crois quelle Ia vu .
This was on a stage .
It 's funny . I thought that being on a stage would be like a nice break
to being , like , outside every day .
But there was something in that dust made - -
- The atmosphere ? - The smoke ?
Something in the smoke . Also the - -
- The ground . - That was in the ground
that I remember , I don 't think I told anybody this at the time ,
- it made me , like - - I couldn 't breathe ... - Oh , wow .
... because I was on the ground the whole time .
It was something that I would breathe it in .
I feel like there were a lot of people that were having that - -
That it was like people were coughing and I was coughing up black stuff .
Sometimes the atmosphere stuff can do that .
This is during COVID , so we were all in masks .
That 's right .
That 's part of why you would 've been more affected by that .
Everyone 's like , " I don 't know what her problem is , we 're fine . "
I feel like I remember asking some of the other , you know ,
people who are also in it , like , I was like , " Is this happening to you ? "
And they were like , " Yeah , there 's something wrong with that . "
And I was like , " Cool . " But you know , we 're all fine .
I just want to mention Stephanie Porter who did our costumes .
Incredible on this Big Beard .
That little punch-in of him was in the reshoots .
It was just - - I had an idea after we shot starting on that bear on his shoulder
that you never really saw , but it was part of the wardrobe .
And then , him turning around in that thing and it was like ...
Thankfully we were doing reshoots and Mike was like ,
" Can we do the thing that was killing me ? "
That was a great reveal .
Ah ...
Aha .
Some of that ended up actually being , even though we shot it
on the stage the first time , it ended up also being outside on location .
All these guys are great . Bennett , who plays Raphael right here .
- So good . - This crew was just ...
These guys who are not in that many scenes in the movie
had to be with us the entire shoot because they were our cover set .
Meaning because we were shooting so much in nature ,
we had to always have a backup plan of a set we would go to in poor weather .
And so the backup was obviously the stage work .
And the stage work was the scenes with them .
Otherwise , they would have just been around for like a week .
But they actually had to be there the entire time .
And Bennett had to do some of his coverage to my double , right ?
- Because we were so lucky ... - Yes .
- ... with not having any COVID shutdowns ... - Yes .
... not a lot of COVID cases . But there was one that we had
and I got close-contacted .
I remember you told me at the beginning of the movie ,
" Please be so careful because you are the only person that if you get COVID ,
this movie will stop . "
You 're like , " I can get COVID and direct from home . "
I could do it virtually .
You were like , " You are the only person . "
And so I was very careful and also , it happened over a weekend ,
so I only had to miss , like , a half a day and then one day , then it was done .
Sors le sauvage . Sortez-lui de la sacrée boîte !
What ?
D 'une façon ou d 'une auftre , tu vas nous aider .
Fais-le saigner .
This cut that happens
is precisely how Billy in the original Predator
cuts himself across the chest .
That was by design . That is the exact angle .
Are you hurt ?
Oh , they tried .
On n 'aurait pas dû amener les chevaux .
Fais-les laire ou la bête ne viendra pas .
- Here we go . - The burned glade .
The burned glade .
This is the one that we did discuss .
We tossed around in the beginning a lot
about whether we would shoot this on stage .
This was , to your earlier question ,
this was the thing that I was , like , I wanted us to do this on stage .
But ultimately , I think we were glad - -
Well , the thing that didn 't allow this , I don 't know if you remember this ,
- the art department had a bill . - Oh , yeah .
We wanted to put dirt - -
Just the dirt on the stage was gonna be $ 3 million .
What ?
And we were like , " Well , we 're obviously not doing that . "
So , yeah , we just had to shoot it outside ,
and I think ultimately everyone 's very happy that we did .
Although , it was a massive - - The biggest challenge we had
was dealing with the smoke here for eight days .
Yeah .
You 'd go to set , and it would look like a bright sunny day .
And you 're like , " Well , this is not the scene . "
And then eventually , you get the smoke in there and you go , " It 's the scene . "
It 's , like , only a scene when the smoke 's there , you know ?
Yeah , yeah .
It was funny , I remember a lot of - -
The smoke would start up ,
and so maybe a gust of wind would come and it would clear out .
So they would amp it up .
But then smoke would come in so strong that even if the camera
was two feet away from our faces , it was so thick , you couldn 't see us .
It felt like a really delicate balance
of getting it thick enough that it makes the scene
but not so thick that you can 't see anything .
Orü posa kwitapÜ .
Naru .
And you guys could not hear each other on - -
No , this , we had earwigs and - -
Even though you were literally a foot away from each other ,
you had earwigs so you could hear each other because it was - -
- Because of the fans . - 'Cause the fans .
The giant fans that were blowing in the smoke .
We couldn 't hear each other over them ,
so we had to have earwigs in to hear each other .
But I think we benefit from - -
See , even in that you see - -
This is a CG hand .
But the face was real and I think it 's one of the best-looking shots of a Predator .
People complain about there being any CG in the movie
when you have Predator because what a great practical effect .
And it is so great when it 's practical .
But sometimes you have CG . Sometimes you can see it . I apologize .
Uh , sometimes you can 't .
This was also partially cut up into
- the original movie . Yeah . - Reshoot original .
No . It doesn 't want bait . It doesn 't hunt that way .
I feel like this was such a crazy set for Dane to walk around in
because he couldn 't see , obviously .
To explain , he was looking out the Predator 's neck .
And this again , with the terrain ,
posed a challenge for everybody in a unique way that he couldn 't see .
- And this was really early on in his - - - Yeah .
When he started shooting with us .
Him figuring out how to , like , navigate an environment .
And the head was on top of his head .
That wasn 't always the case with the Predator design .
But we wanted to make our Predator a little slimmer , less top heavy .
I always felt like the heads could end up feeling a little bobblehead-y .
So we changed some of that stuff around .
So Dane would have to bend over and look down through the eye sockets
in the neck to see .
I think they just basically placed a lot of rock - -
- He would memorize ... - That 's right .
... this rock and this stick and whatever .
He did have an earpiece ...
- He did . - ... so they could tell him ,
- " Move right . Do this . " - Yes .
That 's right .
A lot of these extra fur trappers are family .
I believe our hair stylist and her husband .
That 's right . Her husband is a stuntman .
A stuntman , and they 're all like brothers .
That 's right .
- They 're like this gang . - I was like , " Whose family ? "
- Family to each other . - Yeah .
- Not my family . - I was like , " Your family ? "
That 's what I thought for a second . I was like , " I didn 't know that . "
Yeah . That 's the net ball and the cut clamp .
This is such a great Predator sequence .
Just Predator being super cool .
Yeah , I think it 's such an audience favorite
because you can kind of root for - - Even though the Predator is the villain ,
here 's a sequence you can actually root for him
' cause the fur trappers are actually even more annoying .
They 're worse than the Predator .
At least you sort of understand his motives .
It 's a great moment .
- That - - Yeah . - Biggest laugh .
And also I just want to say that shield was a direct lift
from the video game God of War , that also is a favorite of mine that
- I was playing before making the movie . - That 's cool .
Definitely was exciting to find a way
in which we could enjoy the Predator doing the Predator stuff ,
while not sacrificing the way we feel about our heroes , you know .
And this idea came from - - Jeff was like - -
We were trying to figure out a way to do this sequence visually interesting .
And Jeff was like , " What if the whole scene is like
you 're behind the trees and you 're just seeing people get impacted . "
Which was such a cool idea .
You know , I still wanted to maintain some cool Predator violence ,
but that 's what inspired the thought of , like ,
" Oh , maybe there 's one beat where we 're behind the tree
and it 's the most gruesome thing the Predator does , but it 's all implied .
We see some of it . We don 't see all of it . "
That 's really cool .
Yeah , this is such a cool sequence to root for the Predator .
Mm-hmm .
I have a plan . Get down .
That 's another audience favorite right there .
- That 's a good one . - Big laugh there .
/ saw a beaver that had its legs pinned between two rocks .
This story , how badly did you think this was not going to make it
in the movie as you were doing it ?
Um , I 'm trying to remember .
I just remember thinking like , " Is this working ? "
I just remember thinking , " How do you make this story cool ? "
I felt the same way .
So we kept on changing little lines and trying to figure it out .
But actually , it works and people like - -
- We actually cut it from a cut . - That 's right .
And saw it and was like , " Why isn 't that in the movie ? That 's great . "
I was like , " It is ? " I was so self-conscious about it ,
then we put it in and everyone responded great to it . I was like - -
As he 's typing it in ,
I just wanna point out that is the Close Encounters theme .
You 're trying to figure out , " What should I do ? "
And I 'm like , " I don 't know , let 's do - - " Yeah .
Wait . Naru .
What are you doing , Naru ? Naru , stop !
You 're right . It 's coming back to me .
I remember how insecure you and I both were on the day about that .
I 'm smarter than a beaver .
We were like , " I don 't think this is working . "
" I 'm smarter than a beaver , " is isolated .
- You 're like , " Is this a line ? " - That felt so silly .
It felt so silly , but actually , it 's quite winning , so ...
Yeah , I forget which screening it was ,
but one of our premieres somewhere ,
it either got a laugh or I think it got an applause ,
and I remember being shocked .
I think it was the first one , maybe at Comic Con ...
- I think it was . - ... people applauded ,
and I was like , " Okay , sure . "
This was , at one point ,
scripted to be a bunch of fléchettes that pop out .
It was always - - play with the idea that the expectation
if you 're a Predator fan might be , " Is this the giant explosion ? "
But this is an earlier version of the Predator .
This is before they have all the plasma nuclear weaponry .
Mmm . I love this shot .
I love the way - - ' Cause I think that this , without the discs ,
it just looks so ... Like it 's a totally different movie ,
a totally different genre .
Jeff , what you did there , and then what they were doing ,
and their costumes and the color and everything .
That 's one of those very against type pieces of the movie , is to me .
Every time I see it , I 'm like , " It just feels so real . "
- Here we are . - Here we are .
Okay . So coming up - - Talked about this before - -
This sequence really went back and forth .
And this was - - I grew up on Hong Kong action movies .
I was desperate to make a real melee action scene ,
and had yet to be able to fit that into anything I was working on .
And this was like - - Even in this movie , there wasn 't a lot of excuse to have one .
But here we go . This was a way to unleash .
I have very particular feelings about action choreography
being easy to follow ,
have bits of clever but also being legible .
And we designed the whole scene to be traditional with cuts
so that we could see everything , because the whole fun of the gag
is that Naru was reacting to what 's happening to her
and she 's cleverly improvising like ,
" I 'm gonna grab this then , then grab this . "
And then , " Okay , I can 't . "
And I was nervous about being able to articulate that in a oner .
And then we were told we had one day to shoot the scene
that would have been three days if we did traditional coverage .
So we made it work as a oner , and it 's awesome .
And Sarah 's music is awesome for it , and gets a nice little applause break
at the end that I think is wonderful .
This is one of the ones that in publicity I lied ,
not on purpose
because there were sequences that we would do literally so last minute
that I would be learning them at lunch .
And I remember , this one I was learning at lunch .
And so I was like , " This whole sequence we learned in three lunch breaks . "
It 's a great story though .
And I think on this very Blu-ray that you 're watching right now ,
there 's gonna be some special features of you ...
Learning it in the training camp .
... on mats and cardboard boxes ,
training it over and over and over .
That is not true . Apparently , you brought it back to me .
What it was is that we made changes to the fight
that then had to be learned over the course of several lunches
along with different fight sequences .
But that actually was the fight that we started choreographing the earliest
and practiced the longest .
This cut was your idea , Jeff . Am I wrong ?
Uh , you 're right .
- Yeah . Yeah . - Cool .
And I remember you saying , " Wow , that 's a great idea .
Where is this guy ?
Where 's this idea guy been this whole time ? "
Yeah , this was - - Amber , you questioned this
and you were right . We get away with it .
But you were like , " Why am I not talking ? "
And I was like , " Because it 's a cool Clint Eastwood moment . "
Then heard people 's reactions of , " Do they speak the same language ? "
Which has always been a challenging thing .
- Yeah . - Unnecessarily ,
um , I created confusion because I thought that was a cool stoic thing
and I remember you pointing it out and I should 've listened
- on the day . - Not stoic .
I would have forgotten about that if you hadn 't reminded me
and it doesn 't bother me watching it .
I think it felt weird in the moment .
- Right . - I like the scene a lot .
And props to Bennett . I had this idea .
It was not quite scripted exactly like this .
And I had this idea of - - just before breaking for lunch - -
That the scene should be him describing it all to you
as you 're healing him and all that stuff .
And so we got together with whoever the specialist was on these guns .
And I said , " So how does this work ? " With you guys there ,
or maybe it was just Bennett .
And he described like , " Okay , first you take this
and you put it in the thing and the thing . "
I said , " Okay , so , Bennett , you 'll - - That 's what you 'll say . "
He was like , " Okay . " And I 've heard him talk about this
in other interviews where he was like ,
" So I spent all lunch writing it . "
I think he said he showed it to you and you 're like , " Okay , cool . "
And he 's like , " Is this really happening right now ?
Where I 'm just making - - I 've never - - I don 't understand this . "
- And then ... - That is what happened .
He had a document in his Notes app .
Here .
Last thing .
It 's okay .
Put powder here .
Then pull that back and it will fire .
And he was ,
" I 'm gonna say this , then you 're supposed to say something like that ,
and I don 't know who 's going to tell you that .
Maybe you just figure it out or maybe - - I don 't - -
I wrote something , but I don 't know .
And yeah , that sounds like what we 're doing . "
Sometimes there are things that ,
when they 're last minute , if I were to tell all the departments
and everyone that we 're changing things , it would be a freak-out .
So I let it happen organically .
I 'm like , " Well , you 're - - Okay . " Then , " I just had this idea just now . "
Even though I had it a while ago ,
- but it would have been bad if I hadn 't . - Secrets .
But if you have an idea on the spot ,
then everyone has to flow with it .
I think that 's sometimes better than causing the unnecessary panic .
Exactly .
The other thing to really credit Bennett for
is he had to perform this whole scene with his leg bent back ,
and then buried in the dirt when he was laying there .
This portion , it 's in the dirt .
The leg hole .
There 's like a hole - - there 's like a Bennett leg-sized hole in the ground .
That flop that he does is , to this day , my favorite non-Amber action
physical action in the movie .
I love Bennett 's performance . Bennett 's such a cool dude .
There was a whole cut where we had a fake spider
- crawling over Bennett ... - Ugh .
... that the Predator sees the spider on him and that 's why he - -
It was - - This took a lot of figuring out
of how can we articulate to the audience the rules and what you 're learning ,
and teaching them as well .
I think we landed on the right thing .
But his performance lent itself to having that spider crawling in him ,
it looked like he was freaking out about it .
It can 't see him .
- And there he goes . - There he goes .
I remember so much the weather of each day .
We were there for so long , the weather really changed .
Look at Amber there . There 's a cut that doesn 't make any sense .
- I think it 's coming up . Amber 's there . - Thanks .
No , that 's what 's amazing about it because - -
Maybe we passed it .
Here , there 's a cut that , continuity-wise , makes no sense ,
but it 's one of those things where - - but Angela .
And now you 've - - you just turned around
but then you 're coming from the other direction , like sitting down .
- It might be later . - There 's a few ...
I really wanted to point out because it 's the Angela magic .
There 's a lot of me behind different trees , I remember .
Once again , props to Dakota for being less of a horse rider
than our editor of this movie , Angela .
And trained on this horse
and did 99.9 % of all of this stuff on the horse .
Hey !
That 's him there . He did that jump for real .
- He did the jump for real . - And he was on wires .
- Yes . Yes . - Sure . Yes .
- He did all of this fight . - I remember that .
It is tremendous .
Working at T.J. Maxx one day ,
and then jumping around doing all this stuff the next day .
Isa 'ai !
He added that line , right ?
Yeah , he added that line , which means " cheater . "
And it 's so fun whenever I hear people 's reactions ,
I 'll watch on YouTube , people reacting to this scene
and they all say , " Fuck that guy , he 's cheating . "
They don 't even know Dakota is saying , the next second ,
- exactly what they just said , you know . - That 's so funny .
Run , Naru .
It thinks I 'm the threat .
This is as far as I go .
No more . This is it .
- No . - Bring it home .
That 's why the Comanche language version
of the movie is interesting .
I was so surprised when I watched it .
It really kind of changes the dynamics in ways that feel subtle ,
but then end up being quite important .
I think that feel serious in English , that kind of fly by in Comanche
and then vice versa .
Mm-hmm .
All the Predator blood had to be - -
What was it ? It was glow-in-the-dark - -
- Somehow , was that enhanced ? - It was .
We had different versions of it .
There was some portion of it comes from glow stick fluid .
The glow stick fluid stuff could be on the Predator 's suit ...
- But not on people 's skin . - ... but not on people 's skin .
Even the suit .
There was something different on the suit versus on an object .
" Cause an object , it could be full-on glow stick ,
they didn 't want it to hurt the suit .
It was probably a combination ,
because it was eating through the suit a little bit .
- Oh , wow . - Yeah .
I remember when it would come through
and everyone would be like , " Don 't touch it . "
And it all was a substance that was specifically designed
to then be enhanced .
The stuff on your face at the end is almost entirely ...
You had stuff there , but we designed it better .
- 'Cause it didn 't glow . - It wasn 't great .
That would 've been dangerous .
I remember that was a challenge of figuring out how to do that .
This is a lovely , lovely moment .
This is firing on all cylinders .
I think it 's beautifully shot , beautifully cut , beautifully performed .
Like , he was great . Um ...
- Skye ? - Yeah , Skye . Amazing .
He was one of the least experienced kids in the cast
and had no idea what he would do
and it 's so subtle and you really feel like he 's having a hard time
giving her the news .
And Michelle , who plays your mom , Michelle Thrush ,
gave so many different levels of that performance
that Angela was then able to just give us little slivers of ,
and just seeing that sliver in - -
At its apex of her feeling that pain is so amazing .
No words . I mean , there was dialogue ...
There was dialogue . It 's another one - - An Angela special .
... but it was so unnecessary because the performances were so strong ,
just what they were doing visually .
And the Robert Mirabal music
- also was so beautiful ... - Mournful .
- Gosh , Sarah just did an incredible job . - ... over that sequence .
Right , Sarah worked with Robert Mirabal on that .
Both montages are a combination of Sarah and Robert Mirabal ,
who 's this renowned Pueblo musician .
- Taos Pueblo ? - Taos Pueblo .
Plays lots of different instruments in unique ways .
During the Buffalo Prayer .
The prayer is also Robert Mirabal .
And then we tried it a couple of different places , repurposing it ,
and it worked so well , we thought , " Maybe we can have something like this . "
But in fact , it was exactly that that worked so well in those scenes .
That didn 't actually - - the cut clamp didn 't actually open .
So remember you were like , " Look up . " "
That 's a reshoot too .
And then you 're like , " Not that high . "
" Lower . "
This is a daytime piece of B-roll that we repurposed and - -
- Really ? - Yeah .
Very heavily augmented .
This was partially real - - Like original shoot on stage
- and then reshoot out in the wild . - Mm-hmm .
- Not this shot , but yes , this scene . - The sequence .
- Yeah . - Yeah , we reshot the scene .
This was another COVID - -
We had shot only his side and you guys couldn 't be there together .
Then we also changed the dialogue once we figured out the - -
I don 't know , I think just honing in on what we needed you to say ,
I 'm trying to remember the difference " cause it 's very similar .
I don 't remember the original .
I don 't remember it either .
I just remember we clicked into - -
I remember there were really key moments ,
I think , throughout the movie and not even all of them are in the movie
that you and I clicked into something that felt really magic .
That I would compare it to the magic that we felt in the test audition
when we did the scene with no words , where you and I would go
then reference that , and go like ,
- " Okay , this is ... " - More of that vibe .
More of this .
It was kind of like our little - - I don 't know , like our pinboard
of , like , mental pinboard of going like ,
" These are the bones of what we 're making . "
And this - - It 's funny that it was so late in the game
that it was literally reshoots .
But that was one of those moments , when something just clicked in so good .
I found , in doing reshoots on things , even though you feel like ,
" Oh , my God , we 're changing so much . "
But all of it ends up being the thing that always was the intention .
We just didn 't , at that time , have the way to articulate it .
You know , what 's changed here
was that Amber takes the flower in this scene where
originally , she takes it earlier .
The plan becomes so much clearer . Everything is much more honed in .
And it made the scene so much cooler ,
that you were saying all this stuff to him , and then the whistle .
- Yep . The famous whistle . - A Jhane idea from ...
Different Plains tribes believe if you whistle at night ,
you 're calling bad things or you 're calling spirits
and it 's not a good thing , you 're not supposed to do that .
And so , as part of your wanting to always be open to ideas ,
and especially putting in as much culture as possible ,
she had said like , " What if we do a whistle in the scene
right before the Predator comes ? "
Because she 's calling - - She 's calling it in ,
and also , she kind of , at this point , has nothing to lose .
She wants it to come to her .
And you perform it in a way , if you don 't know that fact ,
it just feels badass .
But if you know it , it 's a whole nother gear .
Jhane came to me and was like ,
" Okay , so you 're going to whistle . "
And we were actually shooting at night outside .
And I was like , " No . "
And she was like , " That 's okay . You 're going to look like you 're going to ,
and we 'll have Rich whistle instead . "
That 's right . You mimed it .
Yeah , I was not going to do that .
Uh , and so I just made my lips look like I was whistling
and then you guys put in a different whistle later .
Also , that stunt , I think , is my favorite stunt of the whole movie ,
where I jump off the branch and onto his shoulders .
That was so fun . That was another wirework day .
I remember you guys training that .
That was so much fun . That was so much fun .
I got to stand up on that ,
it was like a platform , it wasn 't a branch .
A lot of this scene ...
So , this is - - We filled in the gaps in reshoots
and then the stuff that wasn 't was the last day of shooting .
We were on splits .
So we would do mud pit during the evening
and then I would shower at lunch and then come back ,
and we would do Predator scene until the sun came up .
And this is the last day . The sun came up and that was it .
We 'd gotten what we had gotten .
This is what I actually - -
This was what got put together while we were shooting .
- During the original shoot . - The part we did ,
you probably did not train that - - You 're correct .
Which is why we didn 't reshoot this
because we did not , uh , ever get enough time to plan it out .
Um , so we had a lot of hold - -
We had , like , this moment , and this moment , and this moment .
This was a moment we shot on the day .
This is what we died on at the end of the shoot .
Yeah , I remember that .
I remember seeing the sun come up behind him .
Yeah .
- As you 're on the ground ? - Yeah .
I remember thinking , " We 're almost done . "
That was crazy , wrapping during this sequence ,
" cause we had been shooting for so long ,
and the crew and everybody - - And it was so - -
People were clapping and cheering and celebrating and all this stuff .
And I remember you came up to me like , " It felt like a movie in the crowd . "
And you were like , " You know we 're not done , right ? "
And I had - - Because it didn 't feel over to me .
You could sense that I was feeling that , and that 's why you said that .
I was like , " I figured we weren 't done . "
It 's also not wanting to say goodbye .
Petsü !
I love the music here .
I wanna give props to the sound design team .
Craig Henighan , Will Files , that whole crew . And Chris .
The score was also so amplified on that mix stage ,
and this stuff coming together .
It all was so exciting as this came through
and they did so many unique things with sound .
Come on , come on , come on , come on .
Do it
Boy , this thing , man . The way to articulate that this plan
was for her to put that in the thing .
I mean , it started off as a total - - Like , you never saw the helmet .
She took it and then the whole fight scene happens
and this was the reveal , and I thought that was gonna be so great that ,
" Oh , my God , you would not expect . "
It was a giant reveal to everyone
at the same time that it 's revealed to the Predator ,
and people just did not get it .
And so we - - That 's - - all that stuff is like - -
She places it there , she puts it there , and still some people - -
- That scream . That war cry . - The war cry .
I still get shivers . Every time , I get shivers .
Remember I was sick during the reshoots ,
and I texted you in the morning that we were supposed to do that .
I woke up and I had no voice and you were like ,
" That 's fine . Just come to work . Don 't speak all day ,
then we 're going to try it and if it sucks ,
we 'll do it another time . "
And that was the first and only time I spoke that day .
We only did it the one time .
You were like , " I think that 's good . "
And I was like , " I don 't know what just happened . "
It goes to a level that you just don 't quite see in movies .
It was stressful .
It 's funny because we did the Comanche camp stuff
all at the beginning of the movie .
This was a thing that we would do at the beginning of the evening ,
and then we would shoot all night other Comanche camp stuff ,
and then when the sun came up , we would go back
and shoot the scene again .
It felt like twilight zone time warp .
Like we 're just gonna live here for the rest of our lives .
Yeah , we 'd get , like , two shots and then we 'd do something else
- and come back to it . - Mm-hmm .
And the way that you throw that gun to Julian and he catches it .
I didn 't say any - - I don 't even know if you guys - - Whatever .
But it 's exactly the way that Danny Glover catches it
and handles it in Predator 2 .
Which is the allusion that we 're doing , but I didn 't ever reference that .
I didn 't show that . It just so happened that the way it gets tossed
and the way he catches ...
Jhane and Kaz Kipp really spearheaded the construction
of that animated sequence
that was a very late-in-the-game idea .
All the hide art .
A combination of traditional hide art
with artists from all over , um , coming together to put it ...
- All native artists . - ... to build it - -
All native artists . Different tribes .
And our animators , you know , and our title animators working together .
I remember you told me the first time it was playing in Comanche Country ,
and you guys - - you and Jhane were there .
Like from - - You could hear the theaters reacting .
I remember as part of the press tour , we went to Oklahoma
and we did different screenings all at one time .
And that was the first time I saw it in Comanche .
And I didn 't know I was gonna watch the Comanche version .
I remember I saw subtitles come on and I was like ,
" Oh , my God , somebody needs to turn the subtitles off .
This is a disaster . "
- Yay , Amber ! - I was like , " Oh , my gosh . "
Because we introduced the movie each screening , but we only sat in one .
And so , when they were ending , you could , like , hear each one go off ,
and people 's reactions and the clapping ,
and that was really emotional and such a relief .
That was the biggest relief to me , was knowing that the Comanche people
accepted this movie and approved of this movie
and , you know , were proud of it .
It was a huge , um , relief .
Juanita Pahdopony was the very first adviser we had .
Her and her nephew , Dustin Tahmahkera ,
were the first people to look at the script ,
uh , or treatment or wherever we were at that stage ,
it was very early .
She passed away before the movie eventually got to production . Um ...
But she was amazing and it really spoke to how important the movie could be ,
which really put a lot of pressure and inspiration on our shoulders
to achieve something .
Yeah , there 's Craig Henighan and Chris Terhune .
Awesome , awesome sound team .
I was gonna say .
Mark Renton was the compositor who did your arms .
- He saved the day on a variety of things . - Oh ! Well done .
He was the guy you call at the eleventh hour .
Like , " Mark , we need a miracle . "
He was a miracle worker , and specifically - - Yeah , your arm .
He delivered .
It 's funny ' cause I can see that my arms are different .
I remember what they would look like - -
The shape of them and the size and everything .
And I do remember being like - -
It 's something - - a detail only I would notice .
I remember when I saw it , being like , " Oh , they did something . "
But I didn 't think deeply about it .
But I remember thinking , " That is not my arm . "
It 's one of those things where it sets a bad precedent .
Like , " Oh , we can do that ,
so then I 'm gonna not worry about that stuff anymore . "
Like , " What else can we do ? "
I think we just barely get by on it .
So I 'm not being totally serious .
- But , um , it is so impressive . - It does spoil you though .
It really does .
Because the crew was so skilled and we asked a lot .
I was gonna talk about Samiyah Crowfoot
and one of our scenes that really - -
That you and I would reference a lot ,
and that we found is a magic marking point , narratively ,
was the scene that 's not in the movie
with me and Samiyah Crowfoot , who plays the little girl .
Yes . Yes .
Oh , man . That day - - Yeah , the day where you 're kneeling down .
It 's not in the movie .
So the girl that shows up at the end , and she 's in briefly in the beginning
when Dakota comes back with the lion .
There was another scene where you 're telling her
how to string a bow and it was the scene that set up ,
you say , " Don 't get your bow string dirty . "
Um , then , of course , you do , which with the bear and all that stuff .
And I was like , " This is the best scene in the movie . "
And of course it 's not in it .
I remember we were shooting it .
I was like - - Because the wind , it was gorgeous-looking .
We were shooting in Alberta and Stoney Nakoda land .
Props to the land and to the light . Just wherever you go in the world ,
the light of that part of the world brings so much to a movie
or to your photography .
And it was just so special-looking .
And it was the perfect light and the wind was kicking up
through both you and her hair , and it was a really sweet moment .
You don 't expect to see that kind of moment in a movie like this .
There were words but it wasn 't even about the words .
It was just so elemental .
It was like big warrior , little warrior .
Uh-huh .
It was so early on in the movie too
that I feel like it was kind of in the time that Naru was still ,
like , not totally sure about , like , leaving and pursuing this .
I feel like that was part of it , is thinking - -
like looking at her and thinking like , " No , | have to go . "
Then I remember you came - - ' Cause we had had conversations
about , like , you asked me if I wanted to see playback
or watch dailies or anything like that .
And we were like , " I don 't know , probably not . We 'll figure it out . "
And I remember you came to me and it was not a question .
You were like , " Come , I want you to look at this . "
And I was like , " I was - - We 're still shooting it . "
You were like , " No , I need you to look at this . "
And we watched it , and you were like ,
- " This is the movie . " - Mm-hmm .
That 's what you said to me .
And we used that as a marker for something that words can 't describe .
It was what you were doing .
I think it was afforded the ability to be vulnerable
and to be honest .
And I think that it 's like a surprisingly ...
You 're not afforded a lot of gentle moments ,
- emotionally , in this movie ... - Right .
... because there 's a lot of important things happening
and a lot of people have a lot of goals and a lot of opinions .
And so even in the family dynamics , it 's , like , all very purposed .
And I think that was , much like the magical Angela moments ,
it was a moment that was allowed to breathe and to be ,
I think , kind of beautiful and tender and simple and gentle ,
which is not something you really saw from my character
or from just the environment of the movie .
And it 's not in the movie .
And you don 't see it in the movie .
Its spirit lives on and infected the rest of the film .
Because it was so early on .
I think that we did figure out how to like - -
That that was an important part of the movie .
And then that put its way into being able - -
We 're like , " More of that . "
- We needed more of that . - For sure .
Well , guys , here we are . We did it , we made the movie .
Wow .
Can you believe that we - - I was saying this the other day - -
It 's crazy that we spent , like , five or six months there
and that the movie is , like , 90 minute - -
We dedicated over five months to a thing that is 90 minutes ,
but it 's obviously so much more than that .
Yeah . Yeah . By the way , let 's just set the record straight .
You 're now looking at the runtime . The movie is , like , 90 , 92 minutes .
It 's only - - It only climbs up when you watch our ten minute credits ,
like you are right now .
But always people look at the runtime and they go ,
" You made a 100-minute movie - - Whatever . " Like , " No , it 's actually shorter . "
- Like , we really - - It 's quite swift . - Yeah .
- Um - - Yeah . - It is . It feels like a ...
It is one exciting ride .
Mm-hmm .
Well , thank you , Dolby Atmos and DGC Alberta and SAG-ACTRA
and MPA . We really appreciate - -
IATSE , couldn 't do it without you .
You got American Humane society .
Really , really - -
I mean , frankly , they did help us out on this movie .
We couldn 't have made it without them .
And , uh , thank you guys .
- Thank you . - Thank you , Dan .